

## PERFORMANCE SNAPSHOT

15+ years of editing, writing, internal and external communications, and video production expertise.

Able to cultivate employee, board, media, and public supportfor institutional change.

Strong program development to launch co-created content initiatives.

Leads diverse communications teams, in-house and third party.

Point of contact for internal and external organizations and agencies, board, and executive leadership.

### CHIEF COMMUNICATIONS OFFICER

COMMUNICATIONS STRATEGY - CONTENT CREATION - PUBLIC AND MEDIA RELATIONS

EDITORIAL OPERATIONS - CONTENT PARTNERSHIPS - VIDEO PRODUCTION

COMMUNITY AND EMPLOYEE ENGAGEMENT - TEAM LEADERSHIP - MARKET RESEARCH

Innovative communications expert with a track record of developing and implementing multi-faceted, multi-media strategic communication plans that generate employee and public engagement, media coverage, and brand recognition for transforming institutions.

Seasoned in designing content and content partnerships that maximize media attention, brand cultivation and awareness, profit, digital community engagement, and stakeholder support.

Improves employee engagement with feedback loops and cascade communication through multiple platforms.

Proven expertise in various forms of public relations and corporate communications including speech writing, executive messages, web and social media content, blogs, TV and radio spots, case statements, annual reports, and media campaign execution including pitches, press releases, photography, and video.

Effective translator of institutional, scientific, or technical topics into messages that speak to a variety of stakeholders, creating support and engagement where none previously existed.

## SELECT CAREER HIGHLIGHTS

- Developed voice and copy creative for museums during 10-year transformation, funded by capital campaign which exceeded \$135M goal by \$16M.
- Improved visitation to La Brea Tar Pits Museum by 19% over the past 5 years; exceeds record 400K visitors annually.
- Selected for Strategic Planning Committee which developed framework to guide museums for next 5-10 years.
- Selected for participation in "G12" conferences with directors and communications officers from 12 leading international natural history museums.

# **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE & MILESTONES**

### NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM OF LOS ANGELES COUNTY - 2006 to Present

**DIRECTOR OF COMMUNICATIONS, 2009 to Present:** Create and manage implementation of strategic communication plans that accomplish needs of three museums within the Natural History Museum family; create and manage content for those plans on multiple channels and with multiple voices. Develop and execute public relations campaigns to enhance engagement of stakeholders, improve visitation, and bring awareness to institutional events, exhibits, and initiatives. Develop voice, branding, and positioning. Lead a 5-person team in the creation of museum content within publications, websites, blogs, social media, and video production. Create messaging to keep museums and their topics relevant in today's sociopolitical environment and to achieve specific performance objectives, including attendance, revenue, and stakeholder (employees, board, visitors) engagement agals.

- Act as liaison with City of Los Angeles, L.A. County, State of California, and federal agencies, serving as Public Information Officer for partnerships. Co-create digital and print content (annual reports, press conferences, press material, and video segments and spots for L.A. County Channel).
- Spearhead strategic partnerships with peer institutions, universities, and scientific organizations; co-producing outreach platforms, press events, and publications to promote a brand of accessible science that people of any background can participate in.
- Cultivate relationships with media outlets and a pool of writers, editors, bloggers, and producers covering the non-profit, civic, science, government, and education landscapes.
- Realize considerable growth in digital and social media groups, growing Facebook page by 80K+ likes, integrating various other social channels including Instagram, Twitter, and YouTube.
- Earned promotion to Director of Communications based on consistent and high-level performance demonstrated over tenure with the organization.

**EDITORIAL MANAGER, 2006 to 2009:** Authored and edited museum publications and marketing collateral, including member magazine *Naturalist*, all internal communications, trustee reports, annual reports, outreach brochures, website content, and all media releases.

- Developed content for new websites and microsites. Updated advertising copy.
- Created correspondence and wrote talking points for museum director to effectively control the public image of the organization.



### **LOS ANGELES DOWNTOWN NEWS - 2001 to 2006**

**ARTS AND ENTERTAINMENT EDITOR, 2002 to 2006:** Edited content for the newspaper publications, including daily news articles, calendar features, as well as weekly columns. Supervised rotating team of 12 freelance writers, identifying, assigning, and guiding content to drive the publication's relevancy to new residential audiences. Collaborated with a staff of editors, production staff, and photographers, managing layout and design.

- Established and cultivated ongoing relationships with network of emerging artists, cultural and community leaders, government officials, and public relations representatives to ensure accurate and efficient fact-checking.

**STAFF WRITER, 2001 to 2002:** Identified, pitched, and chased down story ideas, working with a variety of sources to complete focused, engaging content. Wrote articles weekly on show, food and event previews, authored reviews, and created profiles for artists and various cultural leaders.

- Provided media coverage at a variety of venues, including cultural programming at major downtown presentations, museums, and galleries.
- Effectively managed schedules for extensive weekly event listings; providing high level general overview of cultural events.

Additional experience includes Freelance Writing for a number of publications and non-profit organizations, Staff Writer for Retroland.com, and Assistant/Story Editor for Pico Creek Productions. Full details available upon request.

## **EDUCATION & TRAINING**

Master's of Communication Management, 2017 (GPA: 4.0)

University of Southern California, Annenbera School for Communications and Journalism

Bachelor of Arts, English, Cum Laude, Dean's Honor List, 1993 (GPA: 3.554)

University of California, Los Angeles

### Seminars through Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County:

Management — Human Resources — Storytelling and Science Communication — Public and Media Notification Systems

### Influencers:

The Tipping Point (Malcolm Gladwell)

Made to Stick (Chip Heath, Dan Heath)

Strategic Ambiguity (Eric Eisenberg)

Our Iceberg Is Melting: Changing and Succeeding Under Any Conditions (John Kotter)

Reframing Organizations: Artistry, Choice, and Leadership (Lee G. Bolman, Terrence E. Deal)

Corporate Communications (Joep Cornelissen)

Spreadable Media (Henry Jenkins, Sam Ford, Joshua Green)

Brand Media Strategy: Integrated Communications Planning in the Digital Era (A. Young)
The Ad Free Brand: Secrets to Building Successful Brands in a Digital World (Chris Grams)
Jab, Jab, Jab, Right Hook: How to Tell Your Story in a Noisy Social World (Gary Vaynerchuk)
Transmedia Branding: Engage Your Audience (Burghardt Tenderich, Jerried Williams)

# **TECHNICAL EXPERTISE**

Microsoft Office Suite - PowerPoint - Adobe Creative Cloud - Google Drive/Docs/Sheets/Alerts - Filemaker Pro - Prezi - Cision - Meltwater - SPSS - HTML - CSS

## **LANGUAGES**

English - Spanish

## **AFFILIATIONS**

Non-Profit Communications and Media Network

SoCal Museums

California Association of Public Information Officials

National Association of Science Writers

American Alliance of Museums

Phi Kappa Phi Honor Society

323-449-7370

KFRIEDRICH990@GMAIL.COM

LINKEDIN.COM/IN/KRISTIN-FRIEDRICH-66362b5